<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="mariansimarro.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="mariansimarro.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-05-13T13:21:11+00:00</updated><id>mariansimarro.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">Beyond Words: Investigating Fine Motor Skills and Verbal Communication in Autism</title><link href="mariansimarro.github.io/blog/2024/beyonwords/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beyond Words: Investigating Fine Motor Skills and Verbal Communication in Autism"/><published>2024-05-21T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-21T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>mariansimarro.github.io/blog/2024/beyonwords</id><content type="html" xml:base="mariansimarro.github.io/blog/2024/beyonwords/"><![CDATA[<p>In this project, we examined the relationship between fine motor skills and expressive verbal abilities in autistic individuals from late childhood through adolescence <a class="citation" href="#simarro_gonzalez_2024">(“Beyond Words: an Investigation of Fine Motor Skills and the Verbal Communication Spectrum in Autism,” 2024)</a>.</p> <p>To start, let’s review the importance of motor development in children. Motor skills lay the foundation for many developmental milestones, including language acquisition, cognitive growth, and social interactions. Research shows that a child’s ability to move and control their body is linked to their development of language, thinking, and social skills. Prior research has found that autistic children often experience delays and challenges in motor skill development. These motor impairments can manifest before social-communicative impairments are formally diagnosed. Despite the fact that up to 87% of autistic individuals exhibit significant motor challenges, these challenges are often overlooked in clinical practice.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="key-findings">Key Findings:</h3> <ol> <li><strong>80% of autistic participants were impaired on at least one motor measure.</strong></li> <li><strong>Significant lower performance was found in tasks requiring speed, dexterity, and coordination.</strong></li> <li><strong>No significant differences were observed in manual motor strength.</strong></li> </ol> <hr/> <p>In the current study, we assessed fine motor abilities in a group of autistic participants aged 8 to 17 and analyzed the associations between these motor skills and a broad range of verbal abilities. Autistic participants exhibited lower performance in dominant hand finger tapping speed, grooved pegboard performance, visual-motor integration (VMI), and VMI motor skills. However, no significant differences were found in grip strength or non-dominant hand finger tapping speed.</p> <p><img src="https://github.com/MarianSimarro/mariansimarro.github.io/assets/102224223/36ba809a-deec-47ef-8d47-6769bcccd45a" alt="Fine Motor Skills Results"/></p> <h3 id="detailed-motor-and-language-correlations">Detailed Motor and Language Correlations:</h3> <ul> <li><strong>Diadochokinesis and Finger Tapping Speed</strong>: A significant negative correlation between diadochokinesis and dominant hand finger tapping speed (<strong>-0.411</strong>).</li> <li><strong>Articulation and Motor Skills</strong>: Significant negative correlations between articulation errors and grooved pegboard performance (<strong>-0.402</strong>), as well as VMI (<strong>-0.381</strong>) and motor coordination (<strong>-0.388</strong>).</li> <li><strong>Expressive Vocabulary and Motor Skills</strong>: A richer expressive vocabulary was significantly correlated with better VMI (<strong>0.384</strong>) and motor coordination (<strong>0.472</strong>).</li> </ul> <blockquote> <p>For the full results, visit <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2024.1379307">https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2024.1379307</a></p> </blockquote> <hr/> <h3 id="possible-explanations">Possible Explanations:</h3> <ul> <li>Motor skills and language development in autism may be linked due to overlapping brain functions.</li> <li>Motor control likely plays a role in language development, particularly in expressive language tasks.</li> </ul> <h3 id="implications">Implications:</h3> <ul> <li>Frequent motor skill assessments are crucial for autistic children.</li> <li>Early motor interventions may support language development in autistic individuals.</li> <li>Further research should explore the neural mechanisms that underlie this motor-language connection.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research"/><category term="autism,"/><category term="motor-skills,"/><category term="verbal-communication"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This post examines the link between fine motor skills and verbal abilities in autistic individuals.]]></summary></entry></feed>